<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An helpe for yong people, preparing them for the worthy receiving of the Lords Supper. By W.L. B.D.</title>
            <author>[W.L., B.D.].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04977</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109302</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844952</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844952</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9811</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04977)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9811)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1278:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An helpe for yong people, preparing them for the worthy receiving of the Lords Supper. By W.L. B.D.</title>
                  <author>[W.L., B.D.].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] H[arper] for Nathaniel Butter at the Pyde Bull, neer St. Augustines Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londn [sic] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9811:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9811:1"/>
            <p>AN HELPE FOR yong people, Preparing them for the worthy receiving of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. L. B. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDN, Printed by <hi>T. H.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter</hi> at the Pyde Bull, neer St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Gate. 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:9811:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9811:2"/>
            <head>Directions for the weak and ignorant Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou firſt directed and taught me, how to teach you; I learned from you, not from my Bookes, what queſtions to inſtruct you in, by obſerving your miſconceits of the firſt &amp; neceſſary grounds of faith, and accordingly I have framed this ſhort Catechiſme: Many other points are needfull for you, as to underſtand the Creed, becauſe elſe you cannot beleeve it: and the ten Commandements, els you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know your ſinnes, nor your duties: and alſo the Lords Prayer, els you cannot tell
<pb facs="tcp:9811:3"/>how to pray: But for help heerein, I referre you to ſome ſhort Catechiſme, where theſe Heads are expounded. Now that you may profit by this take theſe directions: <hi>1.</hi> Learn by heart the places of Scripture brought for proofes, and ponder them in thy mind, till thou underſtandeſt how they proove the point for which they are alledged. This will help thy underſtanding; for it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſay the words, unleſſe thou under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the matter. <hi>2.</hi> Obſerve by the order of the parts, how and in what order God doth ſave men by Chriſt and be you ſure to goe that way. <hi>3.</hi> Obſerve that the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt of Life and Peace in Chriſt, and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by faith do goe before the uſe of the Sacrament, as the Grant or conveyance of Land, doth before the ſealing: and therfore you muſt firſt be in covenant with God, ere you can have right to, or benefit by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament <hi>4.</hi> For the great duty of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your ſelves, doe thus: Lay the ſigne of triall before thee, and then aske thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Is it thus and thus with my ſoule? For example for triall of thy faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, put thy ſelfe to the queſtion: How
<pb facs="tcp:9811:3"/>long have I had faith? Have I indeed been wrought upon by the word of God? What change do I finde in my ſelfe ſince I was a beleever? Spread all thy ſinnes before thee, and then demand, Soul how do I like of this or that ſin? Do I make conſcience of it? or am I willing to enjoy it longer? to make excuſes, and find pretences for the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it? So for obedience and charity, examine thy ſelfe thus; Do I deſire and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour to know, and doe Gods will in all things? Or am I willing to hide mine cies from this or that daty, and to ſhift it off? Do I love the godly becauſe they be godly? Or can I ſco<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne, mock, and deſpite them? Deale faithfully with thy poore ſoule in this duty of examination and triall remembring that before the act of receiving, thou doeſt confeſſe thy ſinnes, and profeſſe before God and that Congregation, that the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them is grievous unto thee, and the burden intolerable: doe not now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble with God and men: be ſure of this, that if thou bring not grace, the Sacrament will put none into thee. He that comes a Iuaas, ſhall go a Iudas: he that comes an
<pb facs="tcp:9811:4"/>unbeleever, or ignorant, or impenitent, ſhall goe away ſo as he came, may in worſe caſe then he came. <hi>5.</hi> And laſtly, Labour for diſtinct knowledge in matters of ſalvation, content not thy ſelfe with ungreauded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, as I thinke ſo, and I hope ſo. Build not on the ſand, but be thou an hearer and a doer of the word, ſo ſhalt thou be able to day hold on eternall life. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="eucharistic_catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:9811:4"/>
            <head>An help for yong People preparing for the worthy receiving of the Lords Supper.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Chriſt, and how he ſeveth us.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW doe you hope to be ſaved?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Who is Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> The ſecond perſon in the bleſſed Trinity, who in the fulneſſe of Time took our nature and became man for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: Gal. 4.4. Ro. 1.3.4. Ioh. 1.14. Mat. 16.16. Ioh. 6.69.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What hath he done to ſave you?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> He died to ſave me from my ſins Ro. 4. 25.1. Cor. 15.3. Eſ. 53.5. Col. 1.20.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Muſt you elſe have died and ſuffred Gods wrath?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Yes; for death is the wages of ſin, and all that are ſinners be under the Curſe. Gal. 3.10. Ro 6.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How can the death of another ſave you?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9811:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Yes, Becauſe Chriſt is our ſuertie, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God to beare our ſins, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what he did and ſuffered in our Name, it is as well as if we had done it our ſelves. Heb. 7.22. Eſ. 42.6. Eſ. 53.6. Gal. 3.1.3. Gal. 4.4.5. 2. Cor. 5.21. 1 Pet. 2.24</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Gods juſtice then muſt be ſatisfied for every ſin?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Yes: God puniſheth the ſins of the Elect in the perſon o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, But the ſins of others that do not believe in their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Ioh. 16.9. Ioh. 11.50. Ioh. 8.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How doth Chriſt ſatifie Gods Iuſtice for us?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Becauſe he anſwered the law for us: Gal. 4.4, 5 Ro. 10.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How did he anſwer the law for u<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By bearing the puniſhment which the law threatned for ſin, and fulfiling the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which the law required of us. Ro 5.19 Gal. 3.13 Ro. 5.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How commeth the death of Chriſt to be ſo available?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Becauſe it was the ſuffering and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of him that is God: Act. 20.28. 1. Pet. 19.1. Cor. 2.8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9811:5"/>
               <head>Of our need of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> DO you ſtand in need of Chriſts right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſſe to ſave you?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Yes: Becauſe I and all the world are wholly corrupted with ſin through Adams fall, and to become ſlaves of Satan and guilty of eternall damnation R 3.10. Gen. 6.5. Ro. 5.12.19. Eph. 22 Ro. 10.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is ſin?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> It is any breaking or ſwerving from the law of God. 1.10.3.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How came ſin into the world?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By the firſt ſin of Adam and Eve in eating the forbidden fruit [God made man upright] Gen. 3.6. Ro. 5.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Are you then a ſinner?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Yes: I was borne in ſin: and do daily Break Gods holy laws, being very prone to evil, and untoward to any thing that is good: Pſ 51.5. Ro. 7.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the puniſhment due to ſinne and ſinners?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> The wrath of God, and eternall death in Hell fire.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> You are delivered from ſin &amp; the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment the of only by Chriſt, as you ſaid?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9811:6"/>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Yes, for his blood clenſeth us from all ſin, 1. Ioh. 1.7. Heb. 9.26.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How can that be, ſeeing you confeſſe that you are ſtill a ſinner?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Yes, though ſin remaine in me, yet I am clenſed from all ſin for two reaſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What the firſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Becauſe I am made free from the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſin (i) from damnation, being juſtified by the blood of Chriſt: Ro. 8.1. Ro. 5.1. Ro. 10.4. Ro. 4.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Why ſecondly?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Becauſe by Chriſt, we are made free from the power of ſin, ſo that ſinne doth not reigne in us: 2. Co. 5.17.20. Gal. 2.17. Ro. 6.6, 114.1. Ioh. 3, 8. Ro. 8.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the means to pertake of Chriſts righteouſneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> ARe all men thus clenſed and ſaved by Chriſts death?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> No: only they that truly beleeve and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of the evill of their doings: Eſ. 1.16. Luke 13.3. Marke 4.17. Luke 24.47.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is faith?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> It is a beleife of the Goſpell, whereby a ſinner truly humbled for ſin, doth truſt and teſt upon Chriſt alone for ſalvation. Or thus;
<pb facs="tcp:9811:6"/>Faith is the relying of an humbled ſoule upon the promiſes of God for ſalvation by Ieſus Chriſt: Eph. 1.13. Eſ. 50.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Muſt the ſoule be firſt humbled and pricked for ſin before it can go to Chriſt for ſalvation?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Yes: for Chriſt came to call ſinners, and to heals the Broken hearted. Mat. 9.13. Eſ. 61.1. Luk. 4.18. 1. Tim. 1.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What promiſes hath God made to the humbled ſoule that believeth and reſteth on Chriſt for mercie?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> God hath ſaid, they ſhall not periſh, but have everlaſting life. Ioh. 3.16. Mat. 11.28.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Is it enough to beleeve and no more?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> No, we muſt alſo repent, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and turne from our fins: Act. 3.19. Mat. 3.8.10. Mar. 1.15.20.21.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is repentance?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> It is, an earneſt diſpleaſure and hatred againſt ſin, whereby we turne from ſin to walk with God in newneſle of life: Mat. 3.8, 10.2. Cor. 7.10.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What promiſe is there made to them that truly repent?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> God will pardon their ſins and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them no more. Eſ. 55.7. Eſ. 1.18. Heb. 10.17. Luke 15.7, 20.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Can we not be Iuſtified before God by
<pb facs="tcp:9811:7"/>our works of obedience, &amp; good endeavors?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> No, becauſe in many things we faile all: and he that is a breaker of the law cannot be ſaved by it. Ro. 3.20 Ro 4.5. Iam. 3.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the true difference between the Doctrine of the law, and of the Goſpell touching ſalvation?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> The law off<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reth ſalvation to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that do fulfil and keep it perfectly in their own perſons R<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How doth the Goſpell off<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r us ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By the righteouſneſſe of another, (i.) of Chriſt, apprehended and applyed to the humbled Soule by a lively faith: Ro 10 9.11. Ro. 4 6.13.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Is true faith then void of good works, and of holineſſe of life?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A</label> No: for then it were a dead faith, and it could not profit us, becauſe whoſoever is in Chriſt is a new creature: Iam 2.14. 2. Cor. 5.17. Iohn 15.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the meaning then when you ſay we are juſtified by faith without works?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> The meaning is, that we are juſtified by Chriſts righteouſneſſe onely, and that there is no need of our works to be joyned with him in that buſines Rom. 3.21.24.28.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> It ſeemes then that God doth receive us into his favour out of his meere mercy in
<pb facs="tcp:9811:7"/>Chriſt alone, Imputing his righteouſneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, and not our ſinnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> It is moſt true: 2. Cor. 5.21. Rom. 4.5.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> The covenant alſo of life and peace is made in Chriſt, to them that believe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent without the condition of perfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> It is ſo. Rom. 5.6. Gal. 2.17.1. Ioh. 2.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> This bleſſed doctrine is taught us in the Goſpell, how elſe is it taught and confirmed to us?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> In the Sacraments.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the nature and uſe of the Sacrament, and of our preparation thereunto.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> HOw many Sacraments be there?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Two only: Baptiſme and the ſupper of the Lord:</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is a Sacrament?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> It is a Seal of the righteouſneſſe of faith: or a token of the Covenant of peace between God and man. Ro. 4.11. Gen. 17.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Say the ſame in other words?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> A Sacrament is an outward and viſible ſigne of an inward and ſpirituall Grace given unto us: as in your Catechiſme:</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is that ſpirituall Grace, whereof
<pb facs="tcp:9811:8"/>the Sacraments be outward ſignes and pledges?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> The favour of God doing away our ſins in and by Chriſt Crucified: 1. Cor. 10.16. 1. Cor. 11.26. Heb. 9.26.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How many parts be there of every Sacrament?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Two: firſt ſome outward bodily ſign of Chriſts own ordaining: ſecondly and ſome ſpiritual Grace or Benefit thereby ſignified:</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the outward ſign in the Lords ſupper?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Bread and wine given and received according to Chriſts appointment.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is ſignified thereby?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> The body and blood of Chriſt Crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the benefit of receiving theſe ſignes?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By them, as by a token and pledge from God himſelfe, the worthy receives is aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that be hath a part and ſhare in Chriſts Death, and ſhall be ſaved thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Do all that come to the Lords Table receive ſuch a pledge of Gods favour?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> No: only they that be worthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers: [the reſt receive meet bread and wine, and ſo profane Gods ordinance, and provoke Gods judgements againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.]</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9811:8"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What muſt we doe that we may be worthy receivers?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> We muſt examine our ſelves whether we have firſt Faith. Secondly, Repentance. Thirdly, New obedience. Fourthly Charity. [For the ignorant and unbeleevers, the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent, diſobedient and uncharitable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, be all of them unworthy receivers.]</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What Faith is required in a worthy Communicant?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> The profeſſion of the true Faith, and the Grace of faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Why is the profeſſion of Faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Becauſe He that looks to partake of Chriſtian Priviledges, muſt know and maintaine the Articles of Chriſtian religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Where be the Articles of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith contained?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> In the word of God, and more ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily in the Creed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Do you underſtand the Creed?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Yes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Why is the underſtanding of thoſe Articles of faith required?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Becauſe if we doe not underſtand the meaning of them, we can never believe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Many underſtand the Creed and yet
<pb facs="tcp:9811:9"/>are unworthy receivers: How may one be aſſured that his knowledge is Sound and Saving?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By two ſignes of ſaving knowledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the firſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> It is a Renuing knowledge, it doth not onely acquainte me with Gods will and waies, But alſo it worketh my heart to Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the ſame. Luk. 7.47. Ioh. 13.17. Ro. 2.20. Ro. 6.17.2. Cor. 3.18.2. Tim. 3.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Whats the ſecond ſigne of ſaving knowledge?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> It is an humbling knowledge, which maketh me more and more to ſee how vile I am, and how unable to doe any thing that is good, and ſo to ſeek ſtrength &amp; helpe from Chriſt. Phil. 3.7.8. Ro. 7.9. Iob 42.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> You have ſaid, that faith is the rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reſting of the humbled ſoule upon Chriſt alone for ſalvation, How will you trie your faith whether it be ſound and lively?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By two ſignes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Whats the firſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> If it hath been wrought in my heart by hearing and knowledge of the word of God. Ro. 10.4.17. [for if we have alwaies had this faith, as carnall perſons ſay they have had, it is a Counterfeite faith: for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally we are borne in unbeliefe, Neither
<pb facs="tcp:9811:9"/>doth faith grow up with our Education, But it is a ſupernaturall gift of Gods ſpirit, wrought in us by the Goſpell Eph. 2.8. Ro. 2.27. Gal. 5 6. Ro. 9.8. Ioh. 3.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Whats a ſecond ſigne of true faith, whereby it may be knowne?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By the fruite of Faith which is to make me walke by the rule of faith (i.) the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo that I ſhall not believe one thing and do the Contrary: [True faith will make one to practiſe what he believeth: elſe tis a dead faith.] <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 2.16.17. Act. 15 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Why is this Gracy of faith required in a receiver?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Becauſe by faith we are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſt, and of the benefits of his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which are ſet forth to us in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: [we muſt bring faith to Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and Gods ſacraments.] Heb. 3.14. Gal. 3.26, the ſecond Grace is repentance: He muſt examine himſelfe in that.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How will you know your repentance to be found?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By two ſignes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Whats the firſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> If I make conſcience of every ſin, even becauſe it is ſin. Luk. 16.10. Act. 24.16. Pſ. 119.128. Gen. 39.9. [if we greive for ſin becauſe of ſhame that is a worldly reſpect,
<pb facs="tcp:9811:10"/>and therefore a wordly ſorrow, But if we greive for our ſins becauſe God is offended, that is a Godly ſorrow, becauſe the reſpect and ground of it is Godly.]</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the ſecond ſigne of ſound re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Amendment: and forſaking of ſinne. [for true loathing and in<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ard hatred of ſin, is accompained with a leaving of it, elſe it is but a mock ſorrow.] Act. 26.20. Ioel 2.13. 2. Cor. 10.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Why is this Grace required in a Commun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cant?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Becauſe God promiſeth nothing to a wicked man, and therefore the ſacrament cannot ſeale nor aſſure him of any mercy in Chriſt. Ro. 25. Mat. 3.7.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the Third Grace required in a worthy receiver?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Care to walke in New obedience. (i.) to abſtaine from evill, and exerciſe our ſelves in that which is Good. Ro. 12.9. Eſ. 1.16.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Why is new obedience required?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Becauſe if we ſay, we have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Chriſt and walke in darkneſſe, we doe but deceive our ſelves. 1. Ioh. 1.6. 1. Ioh. 3.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the ſigne of true obedience?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9811:10"/>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Sincerity (i.) when without doubling of deceit, without diſpenſing or pretences for ſin, we walke upright in the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God. Pſ. 32.2.1. Cro. 28.9.1. Cro. 12.33. [It is a ſpirit without guile, we muſt not hide our eies from any part of Gods will or of our duty.] Pſ. 1 19.80.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the fourth Grace required in a worthy receiuer?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Chriſtian loue and Charity, eſpecially towards all them that love and feare God. 1. Co. 5.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the firſt ſigne of Chriſtian love?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> If we love the Children of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be the Children of God, and fear Him. 1. Ioh. 5.1. 1. Ioh. 3.12.14. Mat. 10.41.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the ſecond ſigne?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> To do our brother no wrong but good if we can. Ro. 13.10.1. Cor. 1.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Whats a Third ſigne?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> If he hath wronged us to forgive him. Eph. 4.32. Mat. 6.14.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is a fourth ſigne?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> A fellow-feeling of our Brothers weal and wo [(i.) if we can rejoyce at the good that befalls our Neighbor, in his wealth, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, gifts, preferment, and graces, as if they had hapned to our ſelves; and on the other ſide, if we can heartly be ſory for the diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:9811:11"/>and loſſes which befall our brethren.] Pro. 24 18. Iob 31.29.30. [eſpecially if we can rejoyce and greive for ſuch good and evills as befall them for Chriſts ſake, Name and cauſe.]</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> Why is ſuch love required in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Becauſe we are members of one Head Chriſt Ieſus: and are all partakers of one Bread, one Hope, one Faith, and therefore ſhould be of one minde and of one heart. Act. 4.32. Ioh. 13.35.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What if after examination we finde not theſe graces to be in our ſelves?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> They that be voide of theſe graces cannot be worthy receivers, But if we finde them to be in us in truth and ſincerity, though not in that meaſure we deſire, wee may and ought to come to the Lords Table.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> By what meanes doth God worke theſe Graces in our hearts?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By the word preached and heard with an honeſt heart: by which alſo they are dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſed. Ro. 14.10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Other Generall queſtions.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> VVHat is the eſtate of man by Creation?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9811:11"/>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> An holy and happy eſtate: for man was at the firſt made like unto God in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe, in goodneſſe and immortallity. He was free from ſinne and miſery.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the eſtate of all men through the fall of Adam?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> An eſtate of ſin and miſery, for wee are all of us originally very ſinfull and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, Being enemies to all Goodneſſe, and prone to all evill, and ſo the objects of Gods wrath, and heires of hell fire.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> What is the ſtate of them that be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> It is an eſtate of holineſſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, which is begun here in the kingdome of Grace, and ſhall be finiſhed in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Glory. [They that are Chriſts, are renewed in knowledge and holineſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Image wherein Adam at the firſt was created, and they are acquitted from the guilt and puniſhment of ſinne by the Blood and Interceſſion of Chriſt and finally, they are intituled to an eſtate of Glory and Immortality with God in Heaven for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore.]</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How muſt we ſerve God here in this life?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> According to his word, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our owne fanſies and deviſes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9811:12"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How muſt we pray to God!</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Only in the Name and mediation of Ieſus Chriſt, praying for ſuch things as are agreable to Gods will to give us.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How ſhall I know that?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By the word of God which ſheweth us what things God hath promiſed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and forbidden.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> How elſe may I know what things I may beg of God in prayer?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> By the Lords prayer, wherein Chriſt hath taught us what to pray for, ſo that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we have need to pray for, or ought to pray for, it is contained in thoſe Petitions.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9811:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9811:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
